Guide to the Robert A. Hamer Papers, 1857-1995 and undated, bulk 1926-1995
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Robert A. Hamer papers 1857-1995 and undated bulk 1926-1995
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Hamer, Robert A.
2.4 linear feet Extent: 1800 Items
Robert A. Hamer was an executive of the Foster and Kleiser Outdoor Advertising Company in California. He worked as a pictorial artist from 1936 to 1953, and as Paint Manager, California Region, from 1956 until his retirement in 1979. The Robert A. Hamer Papers span the years 1857-1995, the bulk of which document the period 1926-1995, and includes photographs, negatives, correspondence, clippings, administrative records, cartoons, scrapbooks, memorabilia, and newsletters. The collection primarily documents Hamer's career in outdoor advertising with the Foster and Kleiser Company in Southern California, and also touches on events in his personal life. The bulk of the collection consists of photographs of Foster and Kleiser billboards in Southern California, covering two time periods, 1926-1935 and 1950-1970. Other photographs document business activities from 1937-1977, including Foster and Kleiser social events; commercial art production; and sign painting. Clients represented in the collection include Anheuser-Busch, C.H. Baker Shoes, and Slavick's Jewelry. Other clients represented are from the alcoholic beverage, food, travel, and automobile industries, and financial institutions.
RL.00494
Language: Material in English
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
All or portions of this collection may be housed off-site in Duke University's Library Service Center. There may be a 48-hour delay in obtaining these materials.
Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library to use this collection.
Provenance
The Robert A. Hamer Papers were received by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library as a purchase in 2007.
Biographical Note
Chronology List
1914 Nov. 5 Born Robert Adolph Hamer, Los Angeles, Calif.
1933 Graduated from Manual Arts High School (Los Angeles, Calif.)
1935 A.A. degree, Los Angeles City College
1936-1953 Pictorial artist, Foster and Kleiser Company (Los Angeles, Calif.)
1947 Married Esther Hankel
1953-1956 Paint superintendent, Foster and Kleiser Company
1956-1979 Paint manager, California region, Foster and Kleiser Company
1979 Dec. 31 Retired, Foster and Kleiser Company
1996 Nov. 5 Died, Orange County, Calif.
Robert A. Hamer served as a member of the Curriculum Advisory Committee with the Los Angeles Trade-Technical College; and as chairman of the California State Division of Apprenticeship Standards for Southern California, during the 1960s and 1970s.
Collection Overview
The Robert A. Hamer Papers span the years 1857-1995, the bulk of which document the period 1926-1995, and include photographs, negatives, correspondence, clippings, administrative records, cartoons, scrapbooks, memorabilia, and newsletters. The collection primarily documents Hamer's career in outdoor advertising with the Foster and Kleiser Company in Southern California, and touches on events in his personal life. The bulk of this collection consists of photographs of Foster and Kleiser billboards in Southern California, covering two time periods, 1926-1941 and 1951-1962. Other photographs document business activities from 1937-1977, including Foster and Kleiser social events; commercial art production; and sign painting. Clients represented include Anheuser-Busch, C.H. Baker Shoes, and Slavick's Jewelry. Other clients represented are from the alcoholic beverage, food, travel, and automobile industries, and financial institutions.
The collection is organized into two series: Business & Personal Files and Photographs & Negatives. The Business & Personal Files Series documents milestones in Hamer's personal and professional life, and contains photographs, correspondence, scrapbooks, administrative records, writings, school newsletters, clippings, awards, cartoon sketches, and memorabilia. Included is a typewritten transcription of correspondence (1857-1880) by Hamer's ancestor, Samuel A. Jackson. The Photographs & Negatives Series makes up the bulk of the collection, and includes photographs and negatives depicting Foster and Kleiser billboards in Southern California. Other photographs document business and personal activities. Included are photographs of model and performer Charo posing with Hamer, accomplished billboard artist Mario Rueda, and other employees.
Large-format print materials have been removed from their original locations and relocated to Oversize Materials.
Subject Headings
Hamer, Robert A. (Robert Adolph), 1914-1996; Anheuser-Busch, inc.; C.H. Baker Shoes (Firm); Foster and Kleiser Company; Slavick's Jewelry (Firm); Advertising -- Alcoholic beverages -- United States; Advertising -- Automobiles -- United States; Advertising -- Financial services industry -- United States; Advertising -- Food -- United States; Advertising, Outdoor; Advertising, Outdoor -- California; Advertising, Outdoor -- United States -- History -- 20th century; Advertising, Outdoor -- Social aspects; Advertising, Outdoor -- United States; Advertising agencies -- United States -- History; Advertising agencies -- California; Advertising executives; Advertising executives -- United States; Billboards -- United States; Billboards-- California; Commercial art; Commercial art-- California; Sign painting; Cartoons (humorous images); Clippings; Memorabilia; Negatives; Newsletters; Photographs; Scrapbooks; California, Southern -- History; John W. Hartman Center for Sales, Advertising & Marketing History
Related Material
Materials related to this collection may be found in other Hartman Center collections, including the Outdoor Advertising Association of America (OAAA) Archives, OAAA Poster Design Collection, OAAA Slide Library, and John E. Brennan Outdoor Advertising Survey Reports.
Contents of Collection
- Business and Personal Files Series, 1857-1995 and undated, (1 box)
  Consists of scrapbooks, photographs, personal and business correspondence, administrative records, print materials, newspaper clippings, awards, ephemera, cartoon sketches, and memorabilia that document Hamer's professional and personal life. Series is organized into three categories: Business files; Personal files; and Scrapbooks. Business files include cartoon sketches that humorously depict Hamer and coworkers. Personal files chiefly document Hamer's early life and retirement years, including a brief biographical essay written by Hamer shortly after his retirement. Correspondence in this category includes a typewritten transcription of letters from 1857-1880 that belonged to Hamer's ancestor, Samuel A. Jackson. Hamer's personal correspondence reflects his interest in the visual arts. Scrapbooks include annotated photographs that document the operational history of Foster and Kleiser in Southern California. Scrapbook contents had been removed from their original binders before acquisition, so no order could be determined. Business Files and Personal Files are arranged alphabetically.
  - Business files, 1936-1979 and undated
    Includes correspondence, administrative records, promotional materials, cartoon sketches, newsletters, and print materials. Cartoon sketches humorously depict Hamer and coworkers. Arranged alphabetically.
    - Cartoon sketches, undated (Box 1)
      - [ Hamer's Little Helpers sketch, undated, removed to Oversize Materials Folder 1] (Box 1)
      - [ #1 Son sketch, undated, removed to Oversize Materials Folder 1] (Box 1)
    - Correspondence, 1953-1979 (Box 1)
    - Industry newsletters, 1947-1958 (Box 1)
    - Los Angeles Trade-Technical College papers, 1965-1978 (Box 1)
    - Office papers, 1965-1967 (Box 1)
    - Personnel records, 1953-1960 and undated (Box 1)
      Includes Hamer's superintendant's school test and employee record; policy memoranda; and employee lists.
    - Promotional materials, undated (Box 1)
    - State Fire Marshal certificates, 1962-1977 (Box 1)
  - Personal files, 1857-1995 and undated (Box 1)
    Consists of correspondence, writings, newsletters, cartoon sketches, clippings, memorabilia, and ephemera. Materials chiefly document Hamer's early life and retirement years, including a brief biographical essay written by Hamer shortly after his retirement. Correspondence includes a typewritten transcription of letters from 1857-1880 that belonged to Hamer's ancestor, Samuel A. Jackson. Hamer's correspondence reflects his interest in the visual arts. Arranged alphabetically.
    - Anaheim Art Association, 1984-1986 (Box 1)
    - Biographical essay, 1985 (Box 1)
    - Cartoon sketches, undated (Box 1)
    - Certificates and awards, 1963-1975 (Box 1)
    - Correspondence, 1857-1995, (2 folders) (Box 1)
    - Postcards, 1903-1914 (Box 1)
    - Memorabilia, 1935-1968 and undated (Box 1)
      - [World War II anti-aircraft training document, undated removed to Oversize Materials Folder 1] (Box 1)
    - Newspaper clippings, 1932-1993 and undated (Box 1)
      - [ Frank and Ernest clipping, 1995, removed to Oversize Materials Folder 1] (Box 1)
    - School newsletters, 1929-1933 (Box 1)
  - Scrapbooks, undated (Box 1)
    Consists of photographs, personal and business correspondence, administrative records, newspaper clippings, awards, and memorabilia that document Hamer's professional and personal life. Included are annotated photographs that document the operational history of Foster and Kleiser in Southern California. Scrapbook contents had been removed from their original binders before acquisition, so no order could be determined.
    - Scrapbook contents, (5 folders) (Box 1)
- Photographs and Negatives Series, 1925-1993 and undated, (3 boxes) (Box 1)
  Consists of photographs and negatives documenting Foster and Kleiser billboards, and also Hamer's personal and professional life. Series is organized into four categories: Billboard photographs; Other business photographs; Personal photographs; and Negatives. Includes 1975 photographs of model and performer Charo posing with Hamer, accomplished billboard artist Mario Rueda, and other employees; and photographs taken May 31, 1960, at a retirement dinner held for Claude Jones. Billboard photographs are arranged alphabetically, and therein chronologically. Other business photographs and Personal photographs are arranged chronologically to show changes over time in Hamer's life and career; and in outdoor advertising.
  - Photographs (Box 1)
    - Billboard photographs, 1926-1962 and undated (Box 1)
      Includes photographs taken during two periods, 1926-1941 and 1951-1962. Markings on workbook photographs indicate they were once organized in binders, and are labeled with street locations of billboards. Workbook photographs seem to have been used in routine work practices. Arranged alphabetically, and therein chronologically by date.
      - Early photographs, 1926-1941 (Box 2)
        - Automobiles and automobile services, 1926-1940 (Box 2)
        - Clothing and accessories, 1926-1931 (Box 2)
        - Entertainment, 1926-1933 (Box 2)
        - Financial institutions, 1926-1931, (4 folders) (Box 2)
        - Food and beverage, 1926-1941, (3 folders) (Box 2)
        - Food, beverage, and services, 1926-1932 (Box 2)
        - Gift shops and department stores, 1926-1935, (2 folders) (Box 2)
        - Home furnishings and appliances, 1926-1931 (Box 2)
        - Shoe stores (Box 2)
          - C.H. Baker shoes, 1926-1932 (Box 2)
          - Other shoe stores, 1926-1931 (Box 2)
        - Slavick's Jewelry, 1926-1931, (2 folders) (Box 2)
        - Travel and miscellaneous, 1926-1931 (Box 2)
      - Small photographs, 1952-1961 (Box 3)
      - Large photographs, 1951-1962 (Box 3)
        - Automobiles and travel, 1951-1962 and undated (Box 3)
        - Entertainment and beer, 1954-1960 (Box 3)
        - Financial institutions, 1954-1962 (Box 3)
        - Food, beverage, and beauty products, 1958-1962 (Box 3)
        - Liquor, 1955-1961 (Box 3)
        - Services and retail, 1954-1962 (Box 3)
      - Workbook photographs, circa 1950s-1960s (Box 3)
        - Beer, 1954 and undated, (2 folders) (Box 3)
        - Beer and liquor, 1959 and undated (Box 3)
        - Blank billboards, 1958-1960 and undated, (2 folders) (Box 3)
        - Financial institutions and non-profit organizations, 1955-1959 and undated (Box 3)
        - Food and beverage, 1958-1959 and undated (Box 3)
        - Service industries, 1959 and undated (Box 3)
        - Travel and miscellaneous, 1959 and undated (Box 3)
    - Other business photographs, 1937-1977 and undated (Box 3)
      Consists of photographs that document Foster and Kleiser business activities, including award ceremonies; dinners; social events; and artists at work. Includes head shots of Hamer and other employees; 1975 photographs of model and performer Charo posing with Hamer, accomplished billboard artist Mario Rueda, and other employees; and photographs taken May 31, 1960, at a retirement dinner held for Claude Jones. Arranged chronologically to show changes over time in Hamer's career; and in outdoor advertising.
      - 1937-1948 (Box 4)
      - 1950-1954 (Box 4)
        - 1951, [ Foster and Kleiser 50th Anniversary photograph, removed to Oversize Materials folder 1] (Box 4)
      - 1955-1957 (Box 4)
      - 1958, Nick Brigante's retirement dinner (Box 4)
      - 1958-1959 (Box 4)
      - 1960 May 31, Claude Jones' retirement dinner (Box 4)
      - 1960 (Box 4)
      - 1961-1964 (Box 4)
        - [ 1962, Hamer's Sloyd Shop [sic] photograph, removed to Oversize Materials folder 1] (Box 4)
      - 1965-1966 (Box 4)
      - 1967-1969 (Box 4)
        - [ 1968, Happy Birthday Los Angeles photograph, removed to Oversize Materials Folder 1] (Box 4)
      - 1970-1971 (Box 4)
      - 1973-1977 (Box 4)
      - Undated, (2 folders) (Box 4)
        - [Undated business photograph, removed to Oversize Materials Folder 1] (Box 4)
    - Personal photographs, 1925-1993 and undated (Box 4)
      Consists of photographs that document Hamer's personal life. Images are chiefly of Hamer, friends and relatives.
      - 1925-1993 (Box 4)
      - Undated (Box 4)
    - Negatives (Box 5)
      - Undated, (4 folders) (Box 5)
- Oversize Materials (Box 5)
  - Business and Personal Files Series, 1857-1995 and undated (Box 5)
    - Business files, 1936-1979 and undated (Box 5)
      - Hamer's Little Helpers sketch, undated (Opaperfolder 1, Box 5)
      - #1 Son sketch, undated (Box 5)
    - Personal files, 1857-1995 and undated (Box 5)
      - World War II anti-aircraft training document, undated (Opaperfolder 1, Box 5)
      - Frank and Ernest clipping, 1995 (Box 5)
  - Photographs and Negatives Series, 1925-1993 and undated (Box 5)
    - Other business photographs, 1937-1977 and undated (Box 5)
      - 1951, Foster and Kleiser 50th Anniversary photograph (Opaperfolder 1, Box 5)
      - 1962, Hamer's Sloyd Shop photograph (Box 5)
      - 1968, Happy Birthday Los Angeles photograph (Box 5)
      - Undated, Business photograph (Box 5)